<appendix id="apx-drag">
<title>Drag and drop</title>

<para>
  The examples in this book have primarily used clicking or key
  presses for user interaction. LÖVE is capable of responding to other
  forms of input, such as gamepads, touch screens, and mouse
  movement.
</para>

<para>
  All of the input functions are documented on
  <link xlink:href="https://love2d.org/wiki">love2d.org&#47;wiki</link>, so mostly you can
  use them as easily as key presses and mouse clicks. However,
  dragging and dropping requires more code than simple if
  statements.
</para>

<para>
  A word of caution&#58; dragging and dropping as the only way to
  interact with an application has accessibility issues. Selecting a
  source and a target with either a click or a series of key presses
  is easier for both users who need a screen-reader or have limited
  mobility or are just plain uncoordinated, while controlling a mouse
  can be difficult. Dragging and dropping also assumes that whatever
  device your application is running on has the ability to process a
  drag and a drop&#59; while most devices today have either a touch
  screen or a mouse, you never know what tech will bring in the
  future.
</para>

<para>
  On the other hand, dragging and dropping is a valid mechanic, and it
  can be useful for some styles of games.
</para>

<section xml:id="apx-dot">
  <info>
    <title>Draggable object</title>
  </info>

  <para>
    For this demo, you need an object that you can drag. In practise,
    this object would be whatever game asset you want your user to
    move. For this example, create a file called
    <filename>dot.lua</filename> and create the essential
    attributes&#58; the X and Y coordinates, the item rotation, and
    whether or not the item is currently moving.
  </para>

<programlisting><![CDATA[
Dot = { }

function Dot.init(x,y)
   local self = setmetatable({}, Dot)
   self.img = love.graphics.newImage("img.png")
   self.x = x
   self.y = y
   self.moving = 0 --is it being dragged
   self.r = 0 --rotation
   return self
end
]]></programlisting>
</section>

<section xml:id="apx-main">
  <info>
    <title>Code</title>
  </info>

  <para>
    The main code doesn&#39;t contain anything you haven&#39;t already
    encountered, it just uses concepts in a way that&#39;s new to
    you.   
  </para>

  <para>
    A mouse press uses collision detection to determine whether the
    user has clicked on a movable object. Even though there&#39;s only
    one movable object in this example, all movable objects are in a
    table, which this code calls <literal>hot</literal>. If the object
    that has been clicked is movable, then it is rotated as a visual
    cue and its <literal>moving</literal> variable is set to
    <literal>1</literal>. The <literal>love.update</literal> function
    ensures that the X and Y values of any moving object in the
    <literal>hot</literal> table are constantly updated.
  </para>

  <para>
    A mouse release action sets the object&#39;s rotation back to its
    original orientation and sets its <literal>moving</literal>
    variable back to <literal>0</literal>.
  </para>
  
  <para>
    Create a second file called <filename>main.lua</filename>, and add
    this code&#58;
  </para>

<programlisting><![CDATA[
require("dot")

hot = {}

function love.load()
   Dot = Dot.init(300,300)
   hot[#hot+1] = Dot
end

function love.update(dt)
   for i,obj in ipairs(hot) do
      if obj.moving == 1 then
	 --DEBUG print(obj.x,obj.y)
	 obj.x,obj.y = love.mouse.getPosition()
      end
   end
end

function love.draw()
   for i,obj in ipairs(hot) do
      love.graphics.draw(obj.img,obj.x,obj.y,obj.r,1,1,79,79)
   end
end

function love.mousepressed(x,y,btn)
   for i,obj in ipairs(hot) do
      if x > obj.x and
	 x < obj.x + obj.img:getWidth() and
	 y > obj.y and
      y < obj.y + obj.img:getHeight() then
	 obj.moving = 1
	 obj.r = 0.3
      end
   end
end

function love.mousereleased(x,y,btn)
   for i,obj in ipairs(hot) do
      obj.moving = 0
      obj.r = 0
   end
end
]]></programlisting>

<para>
  Add any image file, called <filename>img.png</filename> to your
  project and test the code. You should be able to drag and drop the
  object around your game window.
</para>

<para>
  To detect whether one object has been dragged onto another object,
  add more collision detection to this code to detect whether two
  objects are overlapping or not. It&#39;s the same principle as
  detecting mouse clicks.
</para>

</section>
</appendix>
