<chapter xml:id="pic">
  <!-- Ch06 -->
    <title>Graphics</title>

    <para>
      Everyone knows graphics are important for games, but gamers
      acknowledge that there&#39;s something even more important than
      graphics&#58; the game. A good game is a game that&#39;s
      challenging and fun. Graphics, while important, don&#39;t make a
      game.
    </para>

    <para>
      But most modern players expect graphics in their games, and
      given that you&#39;re programming for a graphical game engine,
      you do need graphics. And if you&#39;re going to have graphics
      in your game, you want them to look as good as possible.
    </para>

    <para>
      If you&#39;re not a natural illustrator and don&#39;t have
      access to one, making your graphics look good seems like a tall
      order. And if you&#39;re not familiar with graphic applications
      on Linux, it seems impossible. This chapter teaches you the
      basics of a few of the best Linux graphics applications, and
      provides you with some tips and tricks to make great graphics
      even if you think you have no artistic skill.
    </para>
    
    <section xml:id="pic-genre">
      <info>
	<title>Design by Genre</title>
      </info>

      <para>
	The word <emphasis>genre</emphasis> is an art term meaning a
	category or style. It&#39;s a term meant to be broad and
	nonspecific. If you&#39;re fortunate enough to be able to hire
	an artist to do artwork for your game, then a genre is useful
	to convey to the artist what they should be aiming for. When
	it&#39;s entirely up to you to design the game&#39; graphics,
	a genre gives you a target to aim for when gathering and
	creating all the different artistic elements you need.
      </para>
      
      <para>
	When a the same person programming a game also has to
	design the game&#39;s look and feel, one of the greatest
	concerns is investment of time and effort. After all, you
	can&#39;t afford to just spend your time on art when
	there&#39;s still code to be written. To help you stay on track, keep in mind three basic tenants to successful graphics&#58;
      </para>

      <orderedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>Genre&#58; limit yourself to elements within your
	  declared genre.</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>Consistency&#58; design once, and then duplicate. If
	  you do anything consistently enough, it becomes your
	  <emphasis>style</emphasis>.</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>Minimalism&#58; convey only the most vital information
	  and let your players read between the lines. The less you
	  do, the less you can mess up.</para>
	</listitem>
      </orderedlist>

      <para>
	Before you sit down to create your game art, stop and think of
	a genre to serve as your central design theme. Your theme can
	be anything, just think about what appeals to you or to your
	intended audience. Think in terms of a broad genre. The more
	general your initial concept, the easier it is to hit your
	mark in the end. Much of the frustration that non-artists
	experience when they attempt to make art is because they see
	clearly in their mind what they want, but lack the artistic
	skills to make it happen. Protect yourself by avoiding
	specifics.
      </para>

      <para>
	Here are some examples of some broad themes&#58;
      </para>

      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>Retro 8-bit video games</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>Victorian England</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>Horror</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>Mysteries of the ancient world</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>Saturday morning cartoons</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>Anime or manga</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>Comic book</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>Fantasy</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>Urban</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>Cyberpunk</para>
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>
	It can also be fun to mash up two different genres. Instead of
	settling for just a fantasy game, why not make rock-a-billy
	fantasy? or cyberpunk in the Old West? or a cartoon
	horror game? Mix it up, force yourself to invent a rationale
	for an unlikely combination, and see what happens.
      </para>
      
      <bridgehead>Let the fonts do the talking</bridgehead>

      <para>
	Once you have thought of a genre &#40;or two&#41; for your
	game, go on a font hunt. Fonts are a great way to convey a
	theme quickly, and since there are so many open source fonts
	out there, it&#39;s a one of the lowest investment of effort
	on your part. There&#39;s a font out there for every genre, so
	go find one and bring it into your project to kickstart your
	thematic vision.
      </para>

      <note>
	<para>
	  Fonts are just like everything else you find online or on
	  most computers. They&#39;re <emphasis>licensed</emphasis>
	  for use, meaning that if you find a font you like on a
	  Windows or Mac computer, it&#39;s only licensed for you to
	  use on that one computer. You&#39;re not allowed to
	  redistribute it with your game. So when looking for fonts,
	  make sure its license permits it to be redistributed.
	</para>
      </note>
      
      <para>
	Some of the best open or redistributable font websites
	include&#58;
      </para>

      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    <link xlink:href="https://fontlibrary.org/">fontlibrary.org</link>
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    <link
	      xlink:href="http://slackermedia.info/sprints/">slackermedia.info&#47;sprints</link>
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    <link xlink:href="https://www.fontsquirrel.com/">fontsquirrel.com</link>
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    <link xlink:href="https://www.theleagueofmoveabletype.com/">theleagueofmoveabletype.com</link>
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    <link xlink:href="https://www.dafont.com/">dafont.com</link> &#40;use the site&#39;s filters to view only free and open source fonts&#41;
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>
	If you choose a highly stylized font, then you might need two
	fonts&#58; one for big titles consisting of only a few words
	at a time, and one simpler font that&#39;s easier to read, for
	text that users need to read often or quickly.
      </para>

    <mediaobject>
    <info>
      <othercredit>
	<orgname>Slackermedia</orgname>
      </othercredit>
    </info>
    <alt>Design by font</alt>
    <imageobject>
      <imagedata align="right" width="6in" format="PNG"
		 fileref="img/Ch06_skenlon/fontcollage.png"/>
    </imageobject>
  </mediaobject>

  <para>
    The important thing is that the font or fonts you choose speak
    to your theme. It&#39;s alright if your fonts are a little
    clich&#233; as long as they enforce your genre. If you&#39;re
    not sure of what type of font to use, go look at some movie
    posters or book covers to get an idea of how fonts are used to
    convey the genre of story being told.
  </para>

  <para>
    To install a font&#58;
  </para>

  <orderedlist>
    <listitem>
  <para>
    Open a file manager window and navigate to your
    <filename>Downloads</filename> directory. Most font downloads are
    zipped, so you must unarchive them to install them.
  </para>

  <para>
    If you prefer to work with GUI tools, install
    <application>xarchiver</application> in
    <application>Synaptic</application>.
  </para>

  <para>
    If you prefer to work in a terminal, install
    <application>p7zip-full</application> with
    <command>apt</command>&#58;
  </para>

  <programlisting><![CDATA[
  $ sudo apt install p7zip-full
  ]]></programlisting>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
  <para>
    Next, create a local font folder located at
    <filename>~/.local/share/fonts</filename>.
  </para>
  
  <programlisting><![CDATA[
  $ mkdir -p ~/.local/share/fonts
  ]]></programlisting>

  <para>
    To do this in the GUI, open a file manager by double-clicking the
    Home icon on your desktop. Right-click in any blank space in the
    file manager window. Select <guimenu>Options</guimenu> &#62;
    <guimenuitem>Show Hidden Files</guimenuitem>, and then navigate to
    <filename>.local&#47;share</filename>. In the
    <filename>share</filename> directory, right-click any blank area
    and select <guimenu>New</guimenu> &#62;
    <guimenuitem>Directory</guimenuitem>. Name the new directory
    <filename>fonts</filename>. 
  </para>
  </listitem>
    
  <listitem>
    <para>
      Create a subdirectory in
      <filename>~/.local/share/fonts</filename> for the first letter
      of each font you are installing, and then copy the
      <filename>TTF</filename> or <filename>OTF</filename> files to
      the appropriate place.
    </para>
    
    <para>
      To copy the files, you must first unarchive your font
      downloads. Most font archives can be unarchived with
      <application>p7zip</application> but you can also use other
      unarchiver tools as needed.
    </para>

    <programlisting><![CDATA[
    $ cd Downloads
    $ 7z x arkhamfonts.zip
    $ tar xvf nouveau.tar.bz2
    ]]></programlisting>

    <para>
      Once unarchived, you can copy the files to their destination.
    </para>
    
    <programlisting><![CDATA[
    $ mkdir -p ~/.local/share/fonts/a
    $ cp ~/Downloads/arkhamfonts/ark*ttf ~/.local/share/fonts/a
    ]]></programlisting>

    <para>
      In the GUI, right-click a font archive and select <guimenu>Open
      with</guimenu> &#62; <guimenuitem>xarchiver</guimenuitem>. Drag
      and drop font files from the
      <application>xarchiver</application> window to the directory
      matching the first letter of the font name.
    </para>
  </listitem>
  </orderedlist>
  
  <bridgehead>Color scheme</bridgehead>

  <para>
    The last thematic element you must decide upon is a color
    scheme. While some genres sometimes do have specific colors
    associated with them, there&#39;s a lot of freedom in this aspect
    of design. While the Old West is often associated with browns and
    yellows, and a technical future world often gets painted with
    black and neon green, you can use your own color palette in any
    genre as long as your colors are consistent and somehow relate to
    one another in a pleasing way.
  </para>

  <para>
    The problem for non-artists is finding colors that match.
  </para>

  <para>
    To solve this problem, all you have to do is generate a color
    palette from an existing image. Search the Internet or your own
    hard drive for an image that you like. It doesn&#39;t have to be a
    free-licensed photo and it doesn&#39;t have to match the genre for
    your game, because the image is only going to be used to generate
    colors. Just pick an image that you enjoy looking at.
  </para>

  <para>
    To generate a color scheme from a photograph&#58;
  </para>

  <orderedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>
	Install Image Magick.
      </para>

      <programlisting><![CDATA[
      $ sudo apt install imagemagick
      ]]></programlisting>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
	Download the image to your Pi.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
	Run this Image Magick command, adjusting
	<filename>~/path/to/image.png</filename> to match whatever
	photo you have downloaded&#58;
      </para>
      <programlisting><![CDATA[
      $ convert ~/path/to/image.png -geometry 16x16 -colors 8 \
      -unique-colors -scale 4000% ~/scheme.png
      ]]></programlisting>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
	Take a look at the resulting color scheme.
      </para>
      <programlisting><![CDATA[
      $ display ~/scheme.png
      ]]></programlisting>      
    <mediaobject>
    <info>
      <othercredit>
	<orgname>Slackermedia</orgname>
      </othercredit>
    </info>
    <alt>Color scheme</alt>
    <imageobject>
      <imagedata align="right" width="6in" format="PNG"
		 fileref="img/Ch06_skenlon/scheme.png"/>
    </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
        <mediaobject>
    <info>
      <othercredit>
	<orgname>Slackermedia</orgname>
      </othercredit>
    </info>
    <alt>Source photo by Jess Weichler</alt>
    <imageobject>
      <imagedata align="right" width="6in" format="PNG"
		 fileref="img/Ch06_skenlon/scheme.png"/>
    </imageobject>
  </mediaobject>
    </listitem>
  </orderedlist>

  <para>
    The colors you get back as <filename>scheme.png</filename> are,
    more or less, an average of dominant colors &#40;it&#39;s not
    mathematically sound, but it&#39;s a rough approximation&#41;. Use
    these colors to guide your design. 
  </para>

  <bridgehead>Graphics</bridgehead> 

  <para>
    When it comes to the actual graphics for a game, there are three
    areas of interest you must consider&#58; the background, the
    foreground, and widgets.
  </para>

  <para>
    Widgets and menu screens are where the theme is most obvious,
    because everything is largely static. You can use a thematic
    background, some genre-appropriate buttons, and the stage is set.
  </para>

  <para>
    The background of each level is a good place to set mood and
    tone. It usually needs to be minimal so that it doesn&#39;t take
    attention away from the elements that the player is interacting
    with, but it&#39;s a good opportunity for you to convey elements
    of your theme. For instance, if your game is set in Victorian
    England, then decorating the corners of the background with a
    damask print or a regal design can help convey the
    setting. It&#39;s also a good opportunity to use some of the
    colors of your primary scheme, which can also help set the
    mood&#58; a bright and cheerful background sends a different
    message than a dark one.
  </para>
  
  <para>
    The foreground consists of all the elements your player cares
    about, such as their player character, their enemies, loot,
    tutorial messages, and so on. These elements can also be themed to
    match your color scheme and game theme.
  </para>

  <para>
    Finding graphics can be difficult, but there are online
    repositories of free game art, including&#58;
  </para>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>
	<link xlink:href="https://itch.io/game-assets/free">Itch.io&#47;game-assets&#47;free</link>
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
	<link xlink:href="https://www.gameart2d.com/freebies.html">GameArt2d.com&#47;freebies.html</link>
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
	<link xlink:href="https://kenney.nl/assets">Kenney.nl&#47;assets</link>
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
	<link xlink:href="https://opengameart.org/">OpenGameArt.org</link>
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
	<link xlink:href="https://openclipart.org/">OpenClipArt.org</link>
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para>
    There&#39;s a lot of flexibility in the foreground elements. As
    long as the game <emphasis>world</emphasis> matches your genre, you can drop whatever
    characters, good or evil, into it and gamers won&#39;t think twice
    about it. After all, one of the most famous games of all time is
    ostensibly about the exciting world of plumbing, and yet the main
    enemies are sentient toadstools and turtles. 
  </para>

  <para>
    Even though you may gather game assets from the creative commons,
    you&#39;re still probably going to find that you have to adapt or
    modify them. The Raspberry Pi comes fully equipped for game
    development, graphic design included.
  </para>
</section>

<section xml:id="pic-gimp">
  <info>
    <title>Card Design with GIMP</title>
  </info>

  <para>
    <application>GIMP</application> &#40;GNU Image Manipulation
    Program&#41; is an all-purpose graphics creation application. You
    can use it to modify photographs, textures, existing graphics, and
    combine them all together to provide you with your game assets, or
    you can just create graphics from nothing but your own idea.
  </para>

  <para>
    The barrier to getting started with
    <application>GIMP</application> isn&#39;t artistic skill so much
    as comprehending and learning the many tools
    <application>GIMP</application> has to offer. Entire books have
    been written about it, there are tutorial websites dedicated to
    it, and it has thorough documentation, so this section steps you
    through the process of using the tools that apply to the current
    goal&#58; creating playing cards for Battlejack. Stepping through
    this won&#39;t teach you everything about
    <application>GIMP</application> but it will demonstrate the
    general process and some of the common tools.
  </para>

  <bridgehead>Install</bridgehead>

  <para>
    There are a few different ways to install
    <application>GIMP</application>. The easiest way gets you an old
    version of <application>GIMP</application>, and while there&#39;s
    nothing wrong with that under normal circumstances, you&#39;re a
    software developer now so there&#39;s no reason to settle for
    second best. Instead of installing using
    <application>Synaptic</application> application installer or the
    <command>apt</command> command in a terminal, you can install the
    latest version as described on <link
    xlink:href="https://www.gimp.org/downloads/">gimp.org&#47;downloads</link>.
  </para>

  <para>
    The latest build of <application>GIMP</application> is delivered
    using <application>Flatpak</application>, a software installer
    method similar in spirit to <command>apt</command>. To use
    <application>Flatpak</application>, it must be installed&#58;
  </para>
    
<programlisting><![CDATA[
$ sudo apt install flatpak
]]></programlisting>

<para>
  Once <application>Flatpak</application> has been installed, use it
  to install <application>GIMP</application>&#58;
</para>

<programlisting><![CDATA[
$ sudo flatpak install https://flathub.org/repo/appstream/org.gimp.GIMP.flatpakref
]]></programlisting>

<para>  
  Once <application>GIMP</application> and all of its dependencies
  have been installed, you must log out of the Enlightenment desktop,
  and then log back in so it recognizes updates from
  <application>Flatpak</application>. If you don&#39;t want to do that
  just now, you can launch <application>GIMP</application> manually
  for now, as described on the <link
  xlink:href="http://gimp.org">gimp.org</link> download
  instructions&#58;
</para>

<programlisting><![CDATA[
$ flatpak run org.gimp.GIMP//stable
]]></programlisting>

<para>
  In the future, you can find <application>GIMP</application> in your
  application menu.
</para>

<para>
  The <application>GIMP</application> interface consists of three main
  regions&#58; the toolbox is full of all the tools you use to compose
  graphics, the main window containing any graphics you are working
  on, and contextual docks provides extra options based on what
  you&#39;re doing.
</para>

<para>
  In the first part of this chapter, you defined a theme or a
  combination of themes, and collected suitable assets, such as fonts
  and clip art. <application>GIMP</application> allows you to
  <firstterm>composite</firstterm> them together.
</para>

<variablelist>
  <varlistentry>
    <term>New document</term>
    <listitem>
      <para>
	In the <application>GIMP</application> window, click
	<guimenu>File</guimenu> &#62; <guimenuitem>New</guimenuitem>.
      </para>
      <para>
	In the <guilabel>Create a New Image</guilabel> dialog box that
	appears, set the unit of measure to <literal>mm</literal>. Set
	the image width to <literal>63.5mm</literal> and
	the height to <literal>88.9mm</literal>. These measurements
	are those of a standard US Poker playing card. However, screen
	size and printed size are different, so click the
	<guilabel>Advanced Options</guilabel> link at the bottom of
	the window and set the resolution of your image to
	<literal>100</literal> DPI. Any lower, and your image may look
	too small or pixelated on standard displays. Any higher, and
	your image will be too large to fit on screen.
      </para>

      <note>
	<para>
	  For serious design work, it&#39;s not uncommon to design at
	  a higher resolution just in case you want to also print the
	  designs you create for onscreen display, or to account for
	  the eventual increase in graphic resolution. For instance,
	  as of this writing, it&#39;s common for gamers to own 100
	  DPI monitors sized 1920x1080, but in a few years, 4k
	  monitors, and greater, will be the default. If you design in
	  higher resolutions, you safeguard against increasing
	  resolution, but if you do that during this chapter, you will
	  have to scale the image down in LÖVE.
	</para>
      </note>      
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>

  <varlistentry>
    <term>Color scheme</term>
    <listitem>
      <para>
	So that you have it handy, open the
	<filename>scheme.png</filename> color scheme file you created
	earlier. If you didn&#39;t create a colour scheme file,
	that&#39;s alright, just keep your color scheme in mind.
      </para>

      <para>
	Color selection in a graphics application is a lot like
	variables in programming. It&#39;s something you end up doing
	a lot more often that you think you should have to, although
	<application>GIMP</application> makes it
	easy. <application>GIMP</application> is smart enough to map a
	color scheme to a <emphasis>palette</emphasis>. To see your
	<application>GIMP</application> palettes, go to the
	<guimenu>Window</guimenu> menu &#62; <guisubmenu>Dockable
	Dialogs</guisubmenu> &#62;
	<guimenuitem>Palettes</guimenuitem>. This embeds a new panel
	displaying color palettes, including one called
	<guilabel>Colormap of Image</guilabel>, which is your color
	scheme imported as a palette. 
      </para>
    
      <para>
	Right-click on your palette and select <guimenuitem>Duplicate
	Palette</guimenuitem> to create an editable copy.
      </para>

      <para>
	Double-click the duplicate and give it a name, such as
	<literal>cardscheme</literal>. A named palette becomes
	permanent.
      </para>

      <para>
	You may now close the color scheme file so that only your
	blank card appears in your workspace. Your named color scheme
	remains. Right-click on it and select <guimenuitem>Edit
	Palette</guimenuitem> to open the <guilabel>Palette
	Editor</guilabel> tab to the top. This displays your color
	scheme so you can use it as a reference later, when choosing
	colors in your design.
      </para>
      
      <mediaobject>
	<info>
	  <othercredit>
	    <orgname>Slackermedia</orgname>
	  </othercredit>
	</info>
	<alt>Palette dockable dialogs</alt>
	<imageobject>
	  <imagedata align="left" width="2in" format="JPG"
		     fileref="img/Ch06_skenlon/palette.jpg"/>
	</imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
      
      <para>
	<application>GIMP</application> uses a tabbed interface to
	manage open files, so to get back to your card design,
	click the appropriate tab at the top of the window.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry>
    <term>Text elements</term>
    <listitem>
      <para>
	Eventually you must create cards for each card listed in
	the <filename>deck.ini</filename> file, but this example
	creates a wizard card with a value of 10 to ensure that the
	initial design accounts for a long title and a double-digit
	value.
      </para>

      <para>
	Select the text tool from the tool panel, or press <keycombo><keycap>t</keycap></keycombo> on your keyboard, on the left and click near the top left corner of your card, but don&#39;t start typing anything yet. When you click, a contextual tool-based panel appears below your toolbox. Since the text tool is active, you see options for text. Pick a font within your theme, and set the size to 60 or so.
      </para>

      <para>
	To set the color of your text, click the box labelled <guilabel>Color</guilabel>. A color picker window appears. Its default view is the <application>GIMP</application> color picker, but there are tabs along the top of window. Click the right-most tab to view your custom palette and choose a color for your text. Click the <guibutton>OK</guibutton> button.
      </para>

      <mediaobject>
	<info>
	  <othercredit>
	    <orgname>Slackermedia</orgname>
	  </othercredit>
	</info>
	<alt>Color picker</alt>
	<imageobject>
	  <imagedata align="left" width="4.2in" format="JPG"
		     fileref="img/Ch06_skenlon/picker.jpg"/>
	</imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
      
      <para>
	Now that you have your tool configured, type out the title of
	the card&#58; Wizard. Don&#39; worry if you positioned your
	text too far to the right such that the whole word can&#39;t
	fit&#59; you can fix that afterwards. Press the
	<keycombo><keycap>Esc</keycap></keycombo> key to exit text
	mode.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>


  <varlistentry>
    <term>Time to save</term>
    <listitem>
      <para>
	It&#39;s never too early to start saving your work. To save your document, go to the <guimenu>File</guimenu> menu and select <guimenuitem>Save</guimenuitem>. You can save the document anywhere you please, but it&#39;s best to keep project work together, so saving it into your <filename>battlejack</filename> directory is best. However, <application>GIMP</application> files are a special <filename>.xcf</filename> format intended as an uncompressed master copy, not as a file for everyday use, so in the end you&#39;ll export to <filename>.png</filename> or <filename>.jpg</filename>. Intermediate files that are necessary to create assets but that do not ship with a game are generically called <emphasis>source</emphasis> files. It&#39;s not uncommon to place them in a directory all their own, and then to exclude that directory from your final <filename>.love</filename> package.
      </para>

      <para>
	Using the <application>GIMP</application> save dialog, create a new directory, called <filename>src</filename>, in your <filename>battlejack</filename> project. In <filename>src</filename>, create another directory called <filename>img</filename>, and save your file into it with the name <filename>red-10-wizard.xcf</filename>.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry>
    <term>Moving layer</term>
    <listitem>
      <para>
	When you typed text onto your card, you created a new
	<firstterm>layer</firstterm>. If you don&#39;t see a
	<guilabel>Layers</guilabel> docker in your
	<application>GIMP</application> window, go to the
	<guimenu>Window</guimenu> &#62; <guisubmenu>Dockable
	Dialogs</guisubmenu> menu and select
	<guimenuitem>Layers</guimenuitem> to open it or bring it to
	the top of a docking panel.
      </para>
      
      <para>
	Layers are like sheets of cellophane placed on top of a
	canvas. They&#39;re transparent until you &#34;paint&#34;
	something on them, and even then you can always move or remove
	the layer entirely because you haven&#39;t painted on your
	canvas, but on a transparent layer above it.
      </para>

      <para>
	As long as the text layer is selected &#40;and it is, by
	default, because it was the most recent one you created&#41;,
	you can see its bounding box as a yellow and black
	dotted-line. By default, a layer uses up only as much space as
	it needs, but if you need to make a layer bigger, go to the
	<guimenu>Layer</guimenu> menu and select <guimenuitem>Layer to
	Image Size</guimenuitem>.
      </para>

      <para>
	To move a layer, select the move tool in the tool panel, or press <keycombo><keycap>m</keycap></keycombo>. As always, the tool options panel displays configuration choices for that tool. Click the <guilabel>Move the active layer</guilabel>.  
      </para>

      <para>
	Click on your card and drag your mouse to move the active layer. Position your text where you think the title of each card looks best.
      </para>
     
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>

  <varlistentry>
    <term>Backdrops</term>
    <listitem>
      <para>
	To help the player focus on what&#39;s important, it often
	helps to add backdrops. A backdrop separates important
	information, especially text, from the background image.
      </para>

      <para>
	To add a layer between the background and a foreground layer,
	right-click the background layer and select <guimenuitem>New
	Layer</guimenuitem>. In the <guilabel>New Layer</guilabel>
	window that appears, name the layer
	<literal>backdrop</literal> and set the <guilabel>Fill
	with</guilabel> field to <literal>Transparency</literal> so
	that the layer is filled with an transparent alpha channel.
      </para>

      <para>
	Select the Rectangle Select Tool from the tool panel, or press
	<keycombo><keycap>r</keycap></keycombo> on your
	keyboard. Using this selection tools, select an area around
	the title. It might be hard to tell, but you&#39;re not
	selecting either the title text or the white background behind
	it. You&#39;re selecting a portion of the invisible layer
	between them.
      </para>

      <para>
	Click the top color swatch under the toolbox. In the color
	picker that appears, select the palette tab and select a color
	within your color scheme.
      </para>

      <para>
	Click the <guimenu>Edit</guimenu> menu at the top of the <application>GIMP</application> window and select <guimenuitem>Fill with FG Color</guimenuitem> &#40;FG stands for <emphasis>foreground</emphasis>&#41;.
      </para>

      <para>
	To exit selection mode, press the <keycombo><keycap>Esc</keycap></keycombo> key on your keyboard.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>

  <varlistentry>
    <term>Color code and value</term>
    <listitem>
      <para>
	The card still needs a value. According to
	<filename>deck.ini</filename>, its value is 10. Repeat the
	previous process to create a value indicator.
      </para>

      <para>
	Since Battlejack's opposing sides are differentiated by color
	&#40;red against black&#41;, use red as the backdrop color. If
	you don&#39;t have red in your color scheme, you must
	adapt. You can still use your color scheme as a guide,
	though. RGB colors are defined by three numbers&#58; one
	number, 0 to 255, for red, another for green, and a third for
	blue. These values are visible in the right column of the
	<application>GIMP</application> color picker window. Look at a
	color in your palette and shift its numbers such that the
	highest number is in the color you want to create within the
	same color scheme.
      </para>

      <para>
	For instance, assume you have a green defined in your palette
	with these values&#58; Red 11, Green 14, Blue 8. To produce a
	red similar in &#34;feel&#34;, shift each number one position
	to the left so that the number in the Blue slot now goes to
	Green, the number in the Green slot goes to Red, and the
	number in Red wraps around to Blue&#58; Red 14, Green 8, Blue
	11.
      </para>

      <para>
	The resulting red shade may not be exactly what you want, but
	this trick produces something in the same mood as the rest of
	your color scheme, and you can adjust it manually with one of
	the color wheels in the color picker tabs.
      </para>
        
    <mediaobject>
	<info>
	  <othercredit>
	    <orgname>Slackermedia</orgname>
	  </othercredit>
	</info>
	<alt>Card with text and backdrops</alt>
	<imageobject>
	  <imagedata align="left" width="5in" format="PNG"
		     fileref="img/Ch06_skenlon/cardtext.png"/>
	</imageobject>
    </mediaobject>

      </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry>
    <term>Background image</term>
    <listitem>
      <para>
	The card design is basically finished. It has the requisite
	information on it, so all it needs now is an image. Find an
	image that you feel might represent a wizard. Think
	abstractly. It&#39;s easier to find an image that suggests
	wizardry than to find a free image of exactly what you see in
	your mind&#39;s eye when you think of a wizard.
      </para>

      <para>
	For example, you might be able to find a series of icons for
	fantasy roles consisting of wands, swords, battle axes, and so
	on. Even if you only find five or six icons, you could reuse
	those depending on the broad category of each card &#40;a wand
	for each magic user, a sword for generic fighters, an axe for
	particularly powerful fighters, and so on.
      </para>

      <para>
	Alternately, you can borrow from <productname>Magic&#58; the
	Gathering</productname>, which bases all player abilities on
	five different types of land. Backgrounds for video games or
	even landscape photography is easy to find. Add some
	&#34;flavor text&#34; on the card to explain how the land
	depicted has influenced the wizard that the card represents.
      </para>

      <para>
	The possibilities are endless, so use your imagination. If you
	can&#39;t find suitable images for this project, you can use
	images provided along with the source code for this book. The
	images are from the tabletop game
	<productname>Petition</productname>, designed by the author,
	and illustrated by Nikolai Mamashev in Krita on Linux. All
	assets are provided under the Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike license.
      </para>

      <para>
	To bring in an image, click the layer named
	<guilabel>Background</guilabel>. This layer is the base layer
	of your <application>GIMP</application> document. Click the
	<guimenu>File</guimenu> menu and select <guimenuitem>Open as
	layers</guimenuitem>.
      </para>

      <para>
	The image you choose from the file chooser is imported into
	your document above the <guilabel>Background</guilabel> layer
	but below your backdrops and text. The image may be too large,
	but you can fix that with the scale tool.
      </para>

      <para>
	As needed, select the scale tool from the toolbox, or press
	<keycombo><keycap>Shift</keycap> <keycap>s</keycap></keycombo>
	on your keyboard. Click on the image that you want to resize
	and use the selection bounding box or the dialog box to scale
	the image to better fit into your card design. Press the
	<keycombo><keycap>Return</keycap></keycombo> key or click the
	<guibutton>Scale</guibutton> button to accept the change.
      </para>

      <para>
	Other tools you can use to fit an image into your design
	include the rotate and flip tools. Try them out and see what looks best.
      </para>
      </listitem>
  </varlistentry>

  <varlistentry>
    <term>Integration</term>
    <listitem>
      <para>
	To bring elements of the card design together, and as an
	excuse to learn more <application>GIMP</application> tricks,
	the final step is to make the card look more like an
	intentional design and less like something cobbled together
	from disparate sources. You can try one or none of these
	techniques, depending on what you like in card design.
      </para>

      <para>
	The first technique is to add a subtle drop shadow to the
	backdrop to suggest that the &#34;meta&#34; game information
	is not, itself, part of the wizard. In other words, you&#39;re
	acknowledging that in real life, people don&#39;t walk around
	with banners and titles and a number value assigned to them.
      </para>

      <para>
	To add a drop shadow, select a backdrop layer and then click
	<guimenu>Filters</guimenu> &#62; <guisubmenu>Light and
	Shadow</guisubmenu>. There are currently two different drop
	shadow filters&#58; one is permanent and the other
	&#40;&#34;legacy&#34;&#41; creates a new layer just for the
	drop shadow. Use either one, but remember&#58; less is more. A
	subtle shadow says more than a big, bold shadow that draws
	attention to itself.
      </para>

      <para>
	Another integration technique is to merge the meta information
	of the card with the &#34;flavor&#34; &#40;graphic&#41;. You
	can do that by blending text into the image. First,
	right-click the <literal>10</literal> layer in the <guilabel>Layers</guilabel>
	docker and select <guimenuitem>Text to Path</guimenuitem>.
      </para>

      <para>
	Locate the <guilabel>Paths</guilabel> docker by clicking the
	<guimenu>Windows</guimenu> menu and selecting
	<guisubmenu>Dockable Dialogs</guisubmenu> &#62;
	<guimenuitem>Paths</guimenuitem>. In the
	<guilabel>Paths</guilabel> palette, there is now an outline of
	the text element <literal>10</literal>. The outline is a
	vector path, a mathematical formula that
	<application>GIMP</application> doesn&#39;t see as a graphic
	but as a guide for graphical manipulation. Right-click on the
	path and select <guimenuitem>Path to
	Selection</guimenuitem>. The text on the card is now selected.
      </para>

      <para>
	Navigate back to the <guilabel>Layers</guilabel> docker. Click
	the eye icon to the left of the <literal>10</literal> layer to
	hide the text, and then select the red backdrop layer.
      </para>

      <para>
	With the shape of the <literal>10</literal> still selected,
	press the <keycombo><keycap>Delete</keycap></keycombo> key of
	your keyboard, or go to the <guimenu>Edit</guimenu> menu and
	select <guimenuitem>Clear</guimenuitem>. This erases red from
	your backdrop in the exact shape of a number
	<literal>10</literal>. You can see right through the backdrop
	to the image below.
      </para>

      <para>
	To remove the active selection, go to
	<guimenu>Select</guimenu> and choose
	<guimenuitem>None</guimenuitem> or press
	<keycombo><keycap>Shift</keycap> <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
	<keycap>a</keycap></keycombo> on your keyboard.
      </para>
      </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
</variablelist>

<para>
  There&#39;s a lot more you can do in
  <application>GIMP</application>, so try out some subtle effects,
  brushes, and composite modes. Work in layers so that anything you do
  can&#39;t be undone as needed. <application>GIMP</application> is a
  powerful tool, so investing in a good tutorial book or spending time
  on some tutorial sites is effort well spent.
</para>

<para>
  Of course, you don&#39;t have to use this example as a blueprint for
  your design. Come up with your own ideas, tap into what appeals to
  you, and create it.
</para>

    <mediaobject>
	<info>
	  <othercredit>
	    <orgname>Slackermedia</orgname>
	  </othercredit>
	</info>
	<alt>Card ideas</alt>
	<imageobject>
	  <imagedata align="left" width="5in" format="PNG"
		     fileref="img/Ch06_skenlon/triptych.png"/>
	</imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
</section>

<section xml:id="pic-save">
  <info>
    <title>Exporting from GIMP</title>
  </info>

  <para>
    The native format of <application>GIMP</application> files is a
    multi-layered and uncompressed <filename>.xcf</filename>
    file. It&#39;s intended as a project file for use within
    <application>GIMP</application>. It wouldn&#39;t make sense to use
    it anywhere else, especially not in a LÖVE game. After completing
    each card, you must export it to a common graphic format like PNG
    or JPEG.
  </para>

  <para>
    To export an image from <application>GIMP</application>, go to the
    <guimenu>File</guimenu> menu and select <guimenuitem>Export
    as</guimenuitem>.
  </para>

  <para>
    In the file chooser that appears, navigate to your
    <filename>battlejack</filename> project directory, name the file
    in a standard format, such as
    <filename>red-10-wizard.png</filename>, and then export the image
    to the <filename>img</filename> directory.
  </para>
</section>

<section xml:id="pic-work">
  <info>
    <title>Homework</title>
  </info>

  <para>
    Getting to know <application>GIMP</application> is important if
    you plan on doing graphics work, whether you anticipate creating
    promotional web banners or all the graphics in your game. Spend
    some time getting to understand how
    <application>GIMP</application> works, and enjoy the freedom of
    doing complex graphical work without having to pay a
    &#34;rental&#34; fee each month, the way designers tied down to
    big-name competitors do.
  </para>

  <para>
    There are several other excellent graphic applications on
    Linux. <application>GIMP</application> is good at collage
    &#40;known as <firstterm>compositing</firstterm>,
    professionally&#41;, and can be used for digital painting if you
    download a good set of brushes.
  </para>

  <para>
    Others include&#58;
  </para>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para><application>Inkscape</application> is a vector drawing application, good for precision illustration, layout, and graphics that scale infinitely.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para><application>mtPaint</application> is a bitmap drawing application good for pixel art. It&#39;s a small application that runs very well on the Raspberry Pi. 
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para><application>Krita</application> is a digital painting application. It&#39;s a big application and doesn&#39;t run well on the current Raspberry Pi.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para><application>MyPaint</application> is another digital painting application. For small drawings, it runs on the latest Pi.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>  
</section>
</chapter>
